Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
A couple of months ago asteroid Apophis passed close to the earth
几个月前 阿波菲斯小行星(毁神星)经过地球附近
giving astronomers a good look at its position.
使天文学家仔细地观察了它的位置
For a long time Apophis had been an object of concern
长期以来 阿波菲斯一直是一个令人关注的物体
that had a chance of hitting the earth during some of its future close approaches.
因为在它未来的一些接近地球的过程中 有可能撞上地球
Soon after it was discovered in 2004
在它于2004年被发现后不久
it was determined that there was a 2.7 percent chance that Apophis might hit the earth in 2029.
就确定了阿波菲斯有2.7%的几率将会在2029年撞击地球
But as new data was acquired
但随着新数据的获得
that encounter got ruled out and turned into just a close approach
那次相遇被排除了 并仅变成了一次近距离接触
but that still left many future chances where there was still a risk.
但这仍然留下了许多仍有风险的未来机会
Prior to the recent observations
在最近的观察之前
there was still a one in a hundred thousand chance of an impact this century.
其在本世纪仍有十万分之一的几率发生撞击
Despite years of observations, we had to wait until this most recent encounter
尽管有多年的观察 我们还是不得不等到最近的这次交会
to be sure that this wasn't going to happen.
才能确定撞击不会发生
This is because the close approach to earth changes the orbit of the asteroid
这是因为接近地球的过程改变了小行星的轨道
and the future impact scenarios
而未来的撞击情况
were the result of the orbit being modified by that close approach in 2029
是由于2029年的那次近距离接近而改变了小行星轨道
which meant when Apophis passed near the earth
这意味着当阿波菲斯经过地球附近时
it would have to fly through a very narrow corridor of space
它将不得不飞过一个非常狭窄的太空走廊
to get exactly the right kick from the earth's gravity
以获得来自地球引力正确的一踢
so that this future orbit would ultimately carry it to an impact with the earth.
这样 这个未来的轨道将最终带着它与地球撞击
In astrodynamics we call this a keyhole
在天体动力学中 我们把这称为一个锁孔
and depending upon how far into the future the prediction is
并且取决于预测的未来有多远
a keyhole that leads to a future collision with the earth might only be a couple of hundred meters wide
导致未来与地球碰撞的锁孔可能只有几百米宽
and this makes it exceptionally difficult to say for certain
而这使得我们特别难以确定
whether some of the near-earth asteroids out there could hit the earth in the future.
一些近地小行星是否会在未来撞击地球
The way this works is the earth's gravity bends the orbit a little as the asteroid passes by
其原理是 当小行星经过地球时 地球的引力会使其轨道发生一些弯曲
and then after the asteroid has left the vicinity of the earth the object is in a new orbit.
然后在小行星离开地球附近后 其会处在一个新的轨道上
The closer the object gets to the earth the bigger the deflection the bigger the change in the orbit
当物体离地球越近时 其轨道的偏离越大 轨道的变化越大
so two objects are separated by a small amount
因此 两个物体被以很小的距离分开
can actually experience bigger differences when they emerge on the other side.
当它们在轨道的另一端可能实际上有更大的差异
The encounter orbit can be treated like a hyperbolic orbit with respect to the earth
交会轨道可以被看作是相对于地球的双曲线轨道
and there's a really simple equation that allows you to calculate the amount of deflection
并且有一个非常简单的方程式 可以让你计算出偏转量
based upon the mass of the earth, the velocity of the object at infinity
基于地球的质量 物体在无限远处的速度
and the close approach distance or perigee of the object.
以及该物体距地球最近的距离或者说该近地点
So for something like asteroid Apophis
因此 对于像阿波菲斯小行星这样的物体
which has a relative velocity of about six kilometers per second
它的相对速度约为每秒6千米
and in 2029 we'll approach to about 38 000 kilometers off the earth's center
而在2029年 它将接近距离地球中心约38000公里的地方
or about 31 000 kilometers from the surface.
或者说距地表约31000公里
That encounter is equivalent to a 26 degree turn in the asteroid orbit
这次交汇相当于在小行星轨道上偏转了26度
and that changes the velocity by about 2.7 kilometers per second.
而这将使速度改变约2.7公里每秒
This is exactly like a space probe performing a gravity assist
这完全就像一个太空探测器在进行引力辅助
where a carefully planned encounter with a planet
这种引力辅助会精心策划的探测器与行星的交会
can be used to accelerate a space probe onto a new trajectory
其可以用来加速太空探测器进入一个新的轨道
and that can be used either to leave the solar system
而这可以用来离开太阳系
or maybe it can be used to drop it down closer to the sun
或者可以用来把探测器降到离太阳更近的地方
such as in the case of parker solar probe.
例如帕克太阳探测器
The difference here is that space probe has sensors and equipment on board
这里的区别是 太空探测器上有传感器和设备
to help measure its locati with great precision
来帮助非常精确地测量其位置
while an asteroid position is something that is measured from the ground
而小行星的位置则是从地面上测量的
so our best guess of the actual orbit and close approach might be off by a significant margin.
所以我们对实际轨道和最近接近距离的最佳预测可能会有很大的偏差
So now imagine we do the same math for Apophis
所以现在想象一下 我们对阿波菲斯做同样的计算
but instead of 38 000 kilometers, we move it one kilometer closer
但不是38000公里 而是把它移近1公里
just to see what a difference one kilometer makes.
只是想看看1公里会造成什么不同
Well in that case the gravity of the earth changes the orbit by an extra five centimeters per second
那么在这种情况下 地球的引力使其轨道产生每秒多出五厘米的变化
for being one kilometer closer
因为它离我们近了一公里
which doesn't sound like much
这变化听起来并不多
but over a year it adds up to about 1600 kilometers.
但在一年多后 这一变化加起来大约是1600公里
So the close approach with the earth
因此 与地球的近距离接触
has the effect of amplifying any errors in the orbit after the encounter.
有放大交会后轨道上的任何误差的效果
The uncertainty for Apophis 2029 encounter it used to be hundreds of kilometers
阿波菲斯2029年交会的不确定度曾经是几百公里
but now thanks to concerted campaigns of observation with telescopes and planetary radar
但现在多亏于用望远镜和行星雷达进行的协同观测
the errors are now something like 2.6 kilometers.
现在的误差大约是2.6公里
But the 2029 encounter ruins all our hard work
但是2029年的交会毁掉了我们所有努力工作的成果
by 2036 those 2.6 kilometer error bars have become 99 000.
到2036年 那些2.6公里的误差条已经变成了99000公里
That's in seven years.
这是在7年内
And that's primarily because of the effect of the earth
而且这一变化主要是由于地球的影响
and by 2116 there's another close approach to within 3.5 million kilometers
而到了2116年 又有一次在350万公里以内的近距离接触
but the error bars are now 7 million kilometers
但那时的误差条会是700万公里
and that leaves earth back on the menu with a chance of being hit
而这使得地球又回到了有几率会被撞击的菜单上
albeit with odds of about a million to one so don't worry.
尽管几率大约是一百万分之一 所以不用担心
Also you'll probably be dead then.
另外 到那时你可能已经死了
The error amplification effect gets larger, the closer the object passes to the earth.
物体离地球越近 误差放大效应就越大
So if you have an asteroid say passing one thousand kilometers above the earth
因此 如果你有一个小行星 比如说在地球上方1000公里处经过
that a 1km difference in the position translates to 50 cm/s velocity difference or 16 000 km/y
1公里的位置差会转化为50厘米每秒或16000公里每年的速度差
whereas out at the moon
而在月球上
1km difference in the position only is about 1mm/s in velocity or 30km/y
1公里的位置差只相当于1毫米每秒或30公里每年的速度差
but you know for a long time I thought that orbital mechanics of asteroids were like a well understood problem
但在很长时间里 我都认为小行星的轨道力学是一个很好理解的问题
and it is for the vast majority of asteroids
而且对于绝大多数小行星来说确实如此
but for near-earth objects that are are at risk of impacting the earth
但对于有可能撞击地球的近地物体来说
it does get a lot more complicated than something boring
它确实变得比一些无聊的东西要复杂得多
like a main belt asteroid in the middle of the asteroid belt。
像是小行星带中间位于主带的小行星
Something dull like say asteroid 33 434.
像33号 434号小行星这样枯燥的东西
33号小行星(司瑟星)是第33颗被人类发现的小行星 于1854年10月28日发现
434号小行星(匈牙利)是在主带内侧 相对来说是颗较小的小行星 于1898年9月11日发现
So when we look at objects in deep space
因此 当我们在观察深空的物体时
we can use orbital mechanics to very accurately predict future motion.
我们可以使用轨道力学来非常准确地预测该物体未来的运动
Isaac Newton figured out the laws of motion and the force of gravity centuries ago
艾萨克·牛顿早在几个世纪前就弄清了运动定律和引力
and to a first approximation all objects orbiting the sun follow simple ellipses
并且对于第一近似值 所有围绕太阳运行的物体都遵循简单的椭圆轨道
but then there are perturbations due to things like gravity of the other planets
但是 由于其他行星的引力等原因 会形成一些扰动
radiation pressure from the sun
例如来自太阳的辐射压
re-radiation from the surface of the asteroid
来自小行星表面的再辐射
and sometimes you get outgassing
并且有时你会有放气现象
which can push the asteroid around as volatile materials vaporize
这可能随着挥发性物质的汽化推动小行星
so all of these perturbations can change the orbit over time
所以所有这些扰动都会随着时间改变轨道
but most of them can actually be modeled and accounted for
但其中大部分扰动都可以被模拟和计算出来
especially if you get extra observations to characterize the asteroid.
特别是如果你得到了来描述小行星特征的额外观测数据
Now asteroids are generally discovered by optical telescopes
目前 小行星通常是由光学望远镜发现的
I mean there are quite a few that we don't discover until they suddenly explode over the earth
我的意思是 有很多小行星直到在地球上空爆炸时才被我们发现
but the ones still in deep space that
但那些仍在深空的小行星
we observe calculate orbits for and give numbers to and maybe sometimes names.
我们观察并计算出它们的轨道 并给它们编号 有时还会给它们命名
They are first seen as points of light moving among the stars in telescopes.
在望远镜中 它们最先被看作是在星星之间移动的光点
The word asteroid actually comes from the root aster meaning star-like
小行星这个词实际上来自于aster这个词根 意思是类似星星的东西
and oid meaning asteroid-like
而oid 意思是类似
so the telescopes can take positions of the object on the sky
因此 望远镜可以在天空中对该物体进行定位
and over time as the asteroid moves
并且随着时间的推移 随着小行星的移动
it's possible to then try to fit an orbit to it that matches that observed motion on the sky
就有可能尝试根据它在天空的运动轨迹 为其确定一个相匹配的轨道
but the precision of this is going to be limited by lots of things.
但这一方法的精确性将受到许多因素的限制
First of all we don't have any direct measurements of the distance using a telescope.
首先 我们无法用望远镜直接测量的距离
That you have to infer by finding an orbit that matches the motion in two dimensions
你必须通过找到一个在二维上与其运动相匹配的轨道
and then using that to infer where it must have been in the third dimension.
然后用它来推断它在三维空间的位置
The imaging system isn't going to have perfect positional data
成像系统也不会得到完美的位置数据
either because there are limitations in the optics or limitations in the sensors
因为有光学的限制或传感器的限制
or atmospheric turbulence causing everything to get blurry.
或大气湍流导致一切都变得模糊不清
If you have an image of an asteroid
如果你有一个小行星的图像
say where you have one ten thousandth of a degree precision
比如说你有的图像精度为万分之一度
that's pretty good.
那是相当好的
But at 100 million kilometers away that's only accurate to 300 kilometers.
但是在一亿公里之外 那就只能精确到300公里
Now for objects that come close to the earth we do have another option.
那么 对于靠近地球的物体 我们确实有另一种选择
Planetary radar can get really accurate distance and radial velocity measurements
行星雷达可以得到距离和径向速度的非常精确的测量值
by pinging the asteroid with a signal and looking at the reflection
通过向小行星发射信号并观察信号的反射
and it can actually sometimes even resolve surface structure and features
而且它实际上有时可以甚至解析小行星的表面结构和特征
giving you an idea of the shape
让你对该小行星形状有一个概念
and this gives a huge improvement to the accuracy of the orbit.
而这给轨道的准确性带来了巨大的改善
unfortunately in the last year radar tracking took a bit of a step backwards
不幸的是 在去年雷达追踪出现了一些倒退
when the Arecibo telescope collapsed
由于阿雷西博望远镜的倒塌
and the next best installation I believe is Goldstone
而仅次于它最好的设施 我相信是戈德斯通观测站
戈德斯通观测站(Goldstone Observatory) 是位于美国南加州莫哈韦沙漠的卫星地面站
是深空网络的三个地面终端设施之一 由喷气动力实验室(JPL)运营
and that only has half the range.
而那只有阿雷西博望远镜一半的范围
In the case of Apophis, observers also were able to look for stellar occultations
在阿波菲斯的例子下 观测者们还能够寻找恒星掩蔽现象
that's where the asteroid eclipses a star that's behind it
也就是小行星遮住它身后的一颗恒星
and for the stars you have much better positional information
而对于恒星 你有它更好的位置信息
because we've had missions like Gaia and Hipparcos that are measuring this
因为我们已经有了像盖亚号和依巴谷号这样的任务 正在测量这些信息
盖亚任务(Gaia)是欧洲空间局的空间望远镜
依巴谷卫星(Hipparcos)是欧洲空间局发射的一颗天体测量卫星
so by timing when these stars get eclipses
所以通过计算这些恒星被遮挡的时间
you can get very accurate positional measurements for an asteroid
你可以得到小行星非常准确的位置测量数据
The point that i'm getting at here is that
我在这里想说的是
while we know the equations of motion and we still have imperfect data
尽管我们知道运动方程 我们仍有不完美的数据
and that means that we can't exactly pin down an object's current location.
而这意味着我们不能准确地确定一个物体的当前位置
And any predictions based on this will diverge even further over time
而任何基于此的预测都会随着时间的推移而进一步偏离
and this is fine for most objects that don't come anywhere near the earth or any other planet
这对于大多数不靠近地球或任何其他星球的物体来说是没有影响的
but for those that do the demand on the precision are so much greater
但是对于那些接近星球的物体来说 其所要求的精度都要高得多
because encounters with the earth are so important and have such a big effect on the future orbit
因为与地球的交会十分重要 并且会对其未来的轨道有很大的影响
and if an object has a chance to hit the earth
并且如果一个物体有机会撞击地球
that means that its orbit passes very close to the orbit of the earth
这意味着它的轨道会与地球的轨道非常接近
but even though those two orbits might cross at some point
但是 即使这两个轨道可能在某个点上交叉
the asteroid and the earth won't always arrive at this intersection at the same time
小行星和地球不会总是在同时到达这个交点
like the earth will arrive at this intersection once every year
比如地球每年都会到达这个交点一次
the asteroid will arrive once during every rotation around the sun
小行星会在围绕太阳的每一次旋转中都会到达该交点一次
so whatever the asteroids orbital period is
所以不管小行星的轨道周期是多少
but if they both arrive at the same time or close to the same time
但如果它们在同时到达或接近交点
then a collision or a close encounter occurs.
就会发生撞击或近距离交会
but cross-section of the earth is so much smaller than its sphere of gravitational influence
但地球的横截面比其引力影响范围小得多
so it's much more likely to have a close encounter that changes its orbit than it does to have an impact.
所以相比撞击 它更有可能会进行一次会改变它轨道的近距离交会
The way orbits work by the way means
顺便说一下 轨道的工作方式意味着
if you give something a kick at a certain point in its orbit
如果你在轨道的某一点上给某物体踢一脚
that adjusts the rest of the orbit
这就会调整轨道的其他部分
but not the point where the kick was applied
但不是被踢的那一点
so while an asteroid may have a close approach that changes its orbit, right
因此 虽然一个小行星可能有一个会改变它轨道的近距离接触 对吧
it will still pass through that close intersection point with the earth
它仍然会经过那个与地球较近的交点
no matter how many times the earth kicks it around.
不管地球踢了它多少次
So I guess my point is that
所以我想我的观点是
while there are a bunch of objects out here that come close to the earth's orbit regularly
虽然这里有一堆物体经常接近地球轨道
these close encounters
这些近距离的交会
can't change the orbit by a way that stops them having a chance of coming back to the earth
并不能以一种阻止它们有机会返回地球的方式影响其轨道
that would require them encountering some other planet
那会需要它们其他星球交会
but it does mean that each close encounter has a chance of knocking it onto a trajectory
但这确实意味着 每次近距离交会都有机会将其打入一个轨道
where it could hit the earth in the future.
这个轨道可能会使它在未来撞击地球
but let's be clear the odds of an impact are still fantastically low.
但我们要清楚 发生撞击的几率仍然非常低
Space is big and very empty that's why we call it space.
太空很大 并且非常空旷 这就是为什么我们称之为太空
But if there is a potential impact right there
但是如果有一个潜在的撞击
then the odds tell us that if we discovered such an object
那么概率告诉我们 如果我们发现这样一个物体
that it would have one or more close encounters with the earth
它将与地球有一次或多次近距离交会
before the actual encounter that led to an impact.
在导致撞击的近距离交会之前
The asteroid may have to pass through keyholes in its trajectory
这颗小行星可能要穿过其轨道中的一些关键锁孔
before it gets to the earth
才能到达地球
and that means it might have to pass close to those keyholes
而这意味着它可能必须在接近这些锁孔的地方经过
before we can be sure that it's on a collision course of the earth.
然后我们才能确定它将与地球相撞
From that point it could still be decades away from the actual impact
从这一点来看 它可能离实际的撞击还有几十年的时间
giving us plenty of times to figure out how to deal with that problem
让我们有足够的时间去想办法解决这个问题
but then we'd have missed the best chance to deflect the object from its course.
但那样我们就错过了使该物体偏离其轨道的最佳机会
As I mentioned these close encounters with the earth
正如我提到的 这些与地球的近距离交会
amplify the differences between slightly different orbits
放大了稍微不同的轨道之间的差异
so if you want to change an asteroid orbit say to make it avoid the earth
因此 如果你想改变一颗小行星的轨道 例如让它避开地球
one of the most effective times is to do it before it passes through one of these keyholes.
这么做最有效的时机之一 是在它通过这些锁孔之一前进行
Consider that a keyhole that leads to a future earth impact
考虑到一个导致其未来与地球撞击的锁孔
might only be a couple of hundred meters wide.
可能只有几百米宽
It's much easier to move an asteroid by 100 meters to miss a dangerous keyhole
将小行星移动100米以使其错过一个危险的锁孔
than it is to move an asteroid thousands of kilometers to avoid it hitting the earth.
比把小行星移动几千公里以避免它撞上地球要容易得多
Last year when OSIRIS-REx bopped asteroid Bennu while taking a sample
去年 当欧西里斯号在撞击采集小行星贝努的样本时
it would have given a small push to the asteroid
它会给小行星带来了一个小小的推力
both from the sample tool hitting the surface and embedding itself
这推力既来自于采样工具撞击并插入小行星表面
and from the spacecraft firing its thrusters to back away
也来自于航天器启动推进器向后退去时产生的推力
and the exhaust being reflected from the surface.
和从表面反弹出来的废气
Now this would be a tiny amount of force
那么 这会是一个非常微小的力
but Bennu is quite a small asteroid
但是贝努是一个相当小的小行星
and if you do the math the velocity difference over a year is maybe one meter per year.
并且如果你计算一下 一年内的速度差大概是每年一米
Not very much
不是非常多
but that change will be amplified by the close encounter
但这一变化将被贝努即将发生的近距离交会所放大
that Bennu is going to have with the earth in 2060.
贝努将在2060年与地球近距离交会
And that might make the difference by hundreds of meters per year after that.
而这可能会使之后的差异每年增加数百米
And that was us trying to be sort of gentle as possible on
这是源于我们试图尽可能温和地处理这一过程
because we were trying to protect the spacecraft
因为我们正试图保护航天器
but it's not entirely impossible that there's some distant future
但也不是完全没有可能 在某个遥远的未来
where OSIRIS-REx is responsible for helping Bennu hit the earth
欧西里斯号可能要为帮助贝努撞击地球负责
or by convert potentially stopping Bennu from hitting the earth.
或者转变一下 它有可能阻止了贝努撞击地球
We have the technology to change the orbits of asteroids
我们有技术来改变小行星的轨道
and hopefully we'll see an even more definitive demonstration in the coming years
并且希望我们能在未来几年里能看到一个更可靠的演示
小行星双星重定向测试(Double Asteroid Redirection Test) 该航天器预计于2021年11月发射
当小行星双星重定向测试或飞镖任务从范登堡发射时
when the Double Asteroid Redirect Test or DART launches from Vandenberg
carrying a spacecraft with the mission of making a change to an asteroid orbit.
将携带一个航天器 其任务是改变一个小行星的轨道
One that can be measured by observers on the ground.
一个可以由地面上的观测器测量的轨道变化
To make the change visible they're aiming to modify the orbit of a moon of an asteroid
为了使这一变化可见 他们的目标是改变一颗小行星的卫星的轨道
and that way they're changing the orbit around the parent body
而这样他们就改变了其围绕母体的轨道
which actually makes it much easier to measure this change
这实际上会使测量这种变化变得更加容易
rather than comparing the orbit change of an asteroid flying around the sun
相较对比围绕太阳飞行的小行星的轨道变化
which is a lot further away.
而后者距离要远得多
So while predicting a potentially hazardous impact isn't as easy as you might imagine
因此 尽管预测一个潜在的危险撞击并不像你想象的那样容易
I still believe that humanity is very much up for the challenge
我仍然相信 人类是非常愿意接受这个挑战的
as long as we remain aware of what it takes
只要我们能够意识到我们需要做什么
to track and predict the futures of all the space rocks that regularly fly by the earth.
才能追踪所有定期从地球上飞越的太空石块 并预测它们未来
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[Music]
[音乐]